Guide to the Cottrell and Helean Logging Company (Missoula, Mont.) Records 1945-1971
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Cottrell and Helean Logging Company (Missoula, Mont.) Records
1945-1971
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 176
Cottrell and Helean Logging Company (Missoula, Mont.)
6.0 linear feet and 2 oversize folders
The Cottrell and Helean Logging Company operated in Missoula, Montana. The collection contains general correspondence, financial records, legal documents and maps from 1945 to 1971.
Historical Note
The Cottrell and Helean Logging Company operated out of Missoula, Montana, following World War II until the early 1970s when they discontinued operations. It was an independent logging company that timber to the Anaconda Company in Bonner, Montana.
The collection contains general correspondence, financial records, legal documents and maps from 1945 to 1971.
The collection is divided into four series:
Series I: General Correspondence, 1 folder, 1945-1958
Series II: Financial Records, 6.0 linear feet, 1945-1959
Series III: Legal Documents, 1 folder, 1957, 1971
Series IV: Maps, 2 oversize folders, undated
Materials in Series II, boxes 3-7, are restricted from research access because of personal information on time records.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
These materials were collected and housed by Connie Piquette for an unknown number of years prior to donation to the K. Ross Toole Archives.
Gift of Connie Piquette, 1992.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Logging--Montana--Missoula
Big Blackfoot Milling Company (Butte, Mont.); Missoula White Pine Sash Co.
Maps; Business records--Montana--Missoula
Maps; Labor History; Forestry and Forestry Products
- General Correspondence, 1945-1958; Series I; 1 folder
  The series consists of reminder letters concerning unpaid bills from other companies, workman's compensation claims, copies of outgoing correspondence and information on timber products.
  Materials are arranged chronologically.
  - 1945-1958 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Financial Records, 1945-1959; Series II; 6.0 linear feet
  The series contains check registers, payroll information, assets and liabilities balance sheets, tax returns, and time sheets from Cottrell and Helean Logging Company. Log hauling reports, which contain the car number, number of logs hauled, number of board feet, and totals is in the series. Also in the series is wage schedules that specifies all grades of a certain logging job and the wage scale for that position. A general ledger containing assets and liabilities of the company and two payroll registers, including a saw scale, are in the series.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  The time sheets are closed to research use due to privacy laws that protect social security numbers.
  - Assets and Liabilities Ledger, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Balance Statement, 1945 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Balance Statement, 1946 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Balance Statement, 1952 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Balance Statement, 1953 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Balance Statement, 1959 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Balance Statement, undated (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Check Register, Sept, 1945-May, 1946 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Check Register, Feb, 1948-June, 1948 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Check Register, Sept, 1951-Dec, 1951 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Check Register, Aug, 1952-Nov, 1952 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Company Tax Returns, 1946 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Log Hauling Reports, 1945 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Log Hauling Reports, 1946 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Log Hauling Reports, 1948 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Log Hauling Reports, 1957 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Payroll, Weekly Earnings, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Payroll Register, June 1945-May 1947 (Box OS 8)
    includes saw scale, 1948
  - Payroll Register, May 1947-Feb. 1948; includes saw scale, 1951, 1959 (Box OS 8)
  - Notice of Separation, 1945-1948 (Box-folder 3/1)
    Restricted
  - Payroll, 1945 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Time Sheets, 1945 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Time Sheets, 1945 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Time Sheets, 1946 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Time Sheets, 1946 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Time Sheets, 1946 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Time Sheets, 1946 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Time Sheets, 1946 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Time Sheets, 1947 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Time Sheets, 1947 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Time Sheets, 1947 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Time Sheets, 1947 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Time Sheets, 1947 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Time Sheets, 1947 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Time Sheets, 1948 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Time Sheets, 1948 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Time Sheets, 1948 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Time Sheets, 1948 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Time Sheets, 1948 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Time Sheets, 1949 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Time Sheets, 1949 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Time Sheets, 1949 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Time Sheets, 1949 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Time Sheets, 1949 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Time Sheets, 1950 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Time Sheets, 1950 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Time Sheets, 1950 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Time Sheets, 1950 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Time Sheets, 1950 (Box-folder 7/5)
- Legal Documents, 1957, 1971; Series III; 1 folder
  The series consists of two legal documents, a Forest Service equipment rental agreement and a timber agreement with the White Pine Sash Company of Missoula.
  - Forest Service Equipment Rental Agreement, 1957 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - White Pine Sash Company Timber Agreement, 1971 (Box-folder 2/11)
- Maps, undated; Series IV; 2 oversize folders
  The series consists of unit maps that show the certain areas that the company logged. The five maps in the series are of the Hyde, Fish and Granite Creek areas, and two from the Big Blackfoot Milling Company.
  - Big Blackfoot Milling Company, Granite Creek, Hyde Creek Unit Maps, undated (Box-folder OS 8/1)
  - Fish Creek Unit Map, undated (Box-folder OS 8/2)